<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Paules Church in London and published for the instruction and consolation of all that are heauie harted, for the wofull time of God his generall visitation, both in the citie and in the countrie: and fit for the comfort of Gods children at all times.</title>
            <author>Hooke, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116953</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17477</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17477)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1383:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Paules Church in London and published for the instruction and consolation of all that are heauie harted, for the wofull time of God his generall visitation, both in the citie and in the countrie: and fit for the comfort of Gods children at all times.</title>
                  <author>Hooke, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By E. Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1603]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Christopher Hooke.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED JN Paules Church in London: AND PVBLISHED FOR THE inſtruction and conſolation of all that are heauie harted, for the wofull time of God his generall viſitation, both in the Citie and in the Countrie: and fit for the comfort of Gods Children at all times.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 12. Verſ. 11.12.</bibl>
               <p>No chaſtiſing for the preſent ſeemeth to be ioyous, but grieuous: but afterward, it bringeth the quiet fruite of righteouſneſſe, vnto them that are thereby exerciſed. Wherefore lift vp your handes which hang downe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d your weake knees.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by E. Allde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RJGHT</hi> Honorable, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> Bennet <hi>Knight, Lord Maior of</hi> the Honorable Citie of London: <hi>a proſperous and peaceable Maioralty,</hi> with a plentifull encreaſe of all <hi>God his bleſsings and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> for the effecting thereof, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He hope fayling mee of your honorable preſence at the Croſſe (for I vnderſtand ſince it is not the cuſtome for the Lord elect to come thither) I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt humblie heere offer to your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ading (at your good leaſure) that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then you ſhould haue heard:
<pb facs="tcp:17477:3"/> which, if it anſwere not vnto your expectation, impute (I pray) the defect, partly to the want of the effect of the liuely voyce, which being great in other things, as appeareth by the ſpeeche of <hi>Cteſiphon</hi> to the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> wondring at the Oration of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> which he read vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Quanto magis admiraremini ſi audiſſetis ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum:</hi> By how much more would yee haue marueiled if you had heard himſelfe, is in this of moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, by the ordinance and bleſsing of God, who hath in his wiſdome appoynted faith to bee of hearing. And fauorable pardon I beſeech you all other the imperfections; I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the vtmoſt of my power, to miniſter a word as of inſtruction, ſo eſpecially of conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neceſſary for this woful time; &amp; it was accepted of by your honorable Predeceſſor: And as I haue bene enformed by the reſt
<pb facs="tcp:17477:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the audience then aſſembled, that which the weakeneſſe of my voice could not then performe to all, if by your Honorable acceptance, by this meanes it may be made the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and ſo the more acceptable: I ſhall be much bounden to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, as a chiefe furtherer of my good meaning; If I haue not entred deepe into particulars, and ſearched ſores ſo far as they needed, let it be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of mine ignorance, vnacquainted with publicke affaires, as hauing alwaies liued a priuate life: and the abſence of them to whome ſuch a ſearch eſpecially belonged, whom bebinde the backe I thought it no part of diſcretion, to ſpeake that which by a ſecond report might be made more offenſiue. For concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let mee beſeech you, as I beſought (in this ſermon) your Predeceſſor, to double the care, to double the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,
<pb facs="tcp:17477:4"/> to double the zeale and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of all your Predeceſſors, and that not for the firſt quarter, or for a while, as it were, <hi>quinquennium Neronis,</hi> the firſt fiue yeeres of Nero, but during the time of your whole Maioraltie, euen to the laſt houre thereof: yea, during the whole time of your naturall life, which long may it be, wherein you are to liue by this moſt honorable entrance, in a perpetuall magiſtracie: and hee that is God among Gods, ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance you from this temporall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to an euerlaſting Crowne of glorie, Amen. From my houſe in Deptford this xxxi. of October.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honorable Lordſhips in Chriſt Chriſtopher Hooke</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:4"/>
            <head>A <hi>SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> in <hi>Paules</hi> Church <hi>in London.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 3.1, 2, 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beholde, what maner of loue the Father hath giuen vnto vs, that we ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sonnes of God: for this cauſe the worlde knoweth not you, becauſe it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not him.</p>
                  <p>Dearely beloued, now are we the ſonnes of God, but yet it doeth not appeare what we ſhall be: and we know that when hee ſhall appeare, we ſhall be like him: for wee ſhall ſee him as he is.</p>
                  <p>And euery man that hath this hope in him, purgeth himſelfe, euen as he is pure.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>COnſidering (right honorable and déerely beloued in our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) the heauie hande of GOD, which for our ſinnes hath, and yet doeth lye heauie vpon vs, both in Citie and in Countrie:
<pb facs="tcp:17477:5"/> whereby ſo many as haue either ſence of their owne ſinnes in particular, or of the ſinnes of other ingenerall, or a féeling of their owne afflictions, or a ſympathie &amp; fellow touch of the common calamitie, haue their heads &amp; their harts caſt downe with an extraordinary griefe and ſorrow. Being called to ſupply this place (being the meaneſt and weakeſt of all others:) I haue thought it not amiſſe for the rayſing vp (ſo farre as in me ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) of diſtreſſed hearts and mindes, to handle in your honorable audience, this parcell of Scripture, which miniſtreth vnto vs plentiful matter of ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation &amp; comfort: Herein imitating the example of our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, by whoſe tender compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to all them that are diſtreſſed, calling them vnto him,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> and ſaying: <hi>Come vnto me all yee that labour and are heauie loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will refreſh you,</hi> was fulfilled as S. <hi>Matthew</hi> recordeth, that prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Eſay</hi> concerning him:<note place="margin">Mat. 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>A bruiſed read ſhall he not breake, and ſmoking flax ſhall he not quench.</hi> Hauing alſo for my warrant the commandement of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:17477:5"/> God, vnto the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reſt of Gods Prophets, from the Lord ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Comfort ye, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ye my people ſaith your God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 41.42.</note> 
               <hi>Speake comfortablie vnto Ieruſalem, and crie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, that her warefare is accompliſhed, that her iniquitie is pardoned, and that ſhe hath receiued double from the Lord, for al her ſinnes.</hi> Beſides, when the Lord cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth the Shepheards of Iſrael by his Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 34.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for that they haue not ſtrengthened the weake, nor healed the ſicke, nor bound vp that which was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: It appeareth that it is one eſpeciall parte of our duetie, to bend our ſpeech this way ſo often as occaſion ſhall (as great occaſion at this time doth) offer it ſelfe vnto vs. God therefore aſſiſting me by his heauenly grace and holy ſpirite, for he onely it is that giueth the <hi>tongue of the learned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 50.4</note> 
               <hi>to knowe to miniſter a worde in due ſeaſon, to him that is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:</hi> and you yeelding me your wonted honorable patience and attention, I will endeuour (as the time wil permit) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the inſtructions &amp; comforts of this ſcripture, vnto your godly conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:6"/>
            <p>To procéede therein orderly, I will deuide the whole into two generall parts, euen as it naturally deuideth it ſelfe. The firſt part concerneth the high prerogatiue and dignitie whereunto we who beléeue in Chriſt, and of him are called Chriſtians, are aduanced: namely <hi>to bee called,</hi> or to be <hi>the Sonnes of God,</hi> propoſed firſt in the firſt verſe, with a note of admiration: <hi>Beholde what loue the Father hath giuen vnto vs, that wee ſhould be called the ſonnes of God:</hi> And repeated againe in the <hi>2.</hi> verſe, with an examplification of the time: <hi>Deerely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, now are we the Sonnes of God,</hi> ſignifying by this particle, <hi>Now</hi> the preſent intereſt that we haue in this our high preferment, though the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof in perfection remayneth till the appearance of the Lorde Ieſus, at whoſe appearance it ſhall be made moſt euident: for that then, <hi>We ſhall be like him, and ſee him as hee is,</hi> as he inferreth in the ſeconde parte of this latter verſe.</p>
            <p>And for the further confirmation of this poynte, <hi>that we are the ſons of Gods</hi> The Apoſtle ſheweth, both the Fountain
<pb facs="tcp:17477:6"/> from whence this great mercie floweth vnto vs: to wit, from the loue of God: Secondly, the meanes whereby this his great loue was procured vnto vs: which is his méere grace and frée gift, thorowe Ieſus Chriſt. For the Apoſtle ſayeth, <hi>he hath giuen vs,</hi> for ſo the word ſignifyeth, and ſo it is to be read.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there is no truth ſo plaine but that argumentation may be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt it, and quarrells picked at it: our Apoſtle anſwereth two obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which might be obiected againſt the trueth of this comfortable aſſertion: the one taken from the euil intreatie that we haue in this world. For a man woulde thinke ſince wee are the ſonnes of God, who made the worlde, the heauen, the earth, and al the fulneſſe thereof, that the worlde ſhould know vs to be ſuch, and for our fathers ſake make much of vs. But there is no ſuch matter: for the worlde, as our Sauiour hath fore-tolde vs, careth for it owne: and as for Gods children, becauſe they are not of the world, it reſpecteth not them. To this the Apoſtle anſwereth in the latter ende of
<pb facs="tcp:17477:7"/> the firſt verſe, that the cauſe of the want of better entertainment at the worldes hand, is, becauſe they know not the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as if hee ſhould ſaie, let it neuer trouble you that are Gods ſonnes, that the world know you not, and make no account of you, for it knoweth not the Father that made it, nor the naturall ſonne of the Father, by whom he made it, as this our Apoſtle teſtifyeth: <hi>He was in the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and the world was made by him, but the world knewe him not,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruell though it knoweth not vs that are but his adopted Sonnes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond obiection is taken from a conſideration of our preſent eſtate, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our ſelues, to whom no ſuch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward royaltie appeareth, as wee thinke appertaineth to the ſonnes of ſo high a Maieſtie: whereunto the Apoſtle aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, Firſt by a conceſſion in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond clauſe or comma of the ſecond verſe graunting it to bee ſo, that indeede yet it appeareth not, what wee ſhal be: Secondly, by a certain declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the appoynted time, when we ſhall receiue the perfection of this dignitie, which is
<pb facs="tcp:17477:7"/> when he ſhall appeare, that is, when Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in whom our life is hid, ſhall come to iudge the quicke &amp; the dead: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie which lyeth now buried as it were with ſo great ignominie, ſhall be manifeſted to our endleſſe ioy &amp; comfort.</p>
            <p>Theſe obiections thus aunſwered, whereby the trueth of this principle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth inuincible, <hi>that wee are the ſonnes of God:</hi> The Apoſtle procéedeth to the duetie which wee ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in reſpect of ſo great a prerogatiue, which is the ſecond generall parte of my text, and contained in the third verſe, in theſe words: <hi>And euery man that hath this hope in him purgeth himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5</note> 
               <hi>euen as he is pure:</hi> Wherein firſt he ſheweth, that wee are vncleane of our ſelues, as being conceiued in ſin, &amp; borne in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hauing added therunto infinite thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tranſgreſſions of our owne, both in thought, worde and déede, and therefore haue néede to be purged. Secondly, that this worke of clenſing or purging, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth generally to euery one that hath this hope without exception: Thirdly, how farre forth we ought to labour and
<pb facs="tcp:17477:8"/> to proceede the rein: namely, not to giue ouer, vntil we haue obtained to be pure as he is pure: which becauſe we can neuer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to in this corruptible life, wherein ſinne hangeth ſo faſt on, and ſticketh ſo hard vnto vs,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1</note> he meaneth that we ſhould apply the whole courſe of our life, vnto an earneſt ſtudie of ſanctification and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>So that the ſumme of the whole is, that God of his méere loue to vs-warde in Ieſus Chriſt, hath adopted vs in and thorow him, to be his ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and that this is not a preferment of hereafter onely to be, but a preſent prerogatiue and dignitie how-euer the world doth not ſo acknowledge vs, nor the excellencie therof ſéemeth as yet ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to our ſelues:<note place="margin">2, Cor. 7.1</note> and therefore it is our parts and dueties, as our Father is holy, ſo alſo to be holy: and therefore to purge our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and of the Spirit, and to growe vp into full holineſſe in the feare of God, as the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> exhorteth. And to ſhew foorth as S. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 2.9.</note> the vertues of him, that is, of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:17477:8"/> heauenly Father, which hath called vs out of darkeneſſe into his marueilous light.</p>
            <p>Now to handle euery part and poynt in his owne order, ſo farre forth as the time will permit: we haue firſt to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der more at large of this our high calling and prerogatiue, and therein to obſerue howe by other places of Scripture, both it is confirmed and alſo amplifyed. This our Euangeliſt teſtifyeth: <hi>That ſo many as receiued Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>to them he gaue this prerogatiue, to be the ſonnes of God, euen to them that beleeue in his name.</hi> The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Ye are all the ſonnes of God by faith in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. he alleageth the teſtimonie of God himſelfe out of the Prophet <hi>Eſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>I will be your God, and you ſhall be my Sonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</hi> Our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour when he teacheth vs in the 6. of <hi>Matthew</hi> to pray thus: <hi>O our Father which art in Heauen,</hi> thereby plainely ſignifyeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that we are Gods children, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing alſo the holy ſpirit of God teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp; witneſſeth vnto our ſpirits, in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldning
<pb facs="tcp:17477:9"/> vs to crie <hi>Abba Father:</hi> So that if wee beleeue theſe Scriptures which are ſo plaine and pregnant in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, wee neede make no doubt of this great mercie of God vnto vs, in making vs to be his ſonnes.</p>
            <p>But not onely thus ſimplie and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely the Scripture ſetteth downe, <hi>that we are the Sonnes of God:</hi> but it ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth the ſame by gradation vnto the higheſt degrée. In the <hi>4. Galatians,</hi> at the <hi>7.</hi> verſe, the Apoſtle amplifyeth it: Firſt, reiecting or renouncing vtterly that ſeruile eſtate wherin we once were: ſaying, <hi>Wherefore thou art no more a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant:</hi> and then peremptorily ſetting it downe, <hi>but a ſonne.</hi> There-upon hee ariſeth a ſteppe further, <hi>If thou be a ſonne, thou art alſo the heire of God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Chriſt:</hi> And moſt ſwéetely in the <hi>8.</hi> to the <hi>Ron. 17.</hi> he reaſoneth thus: <hi>If we be children, we are alſo heires,</hi> which is one ſteppe higher, <hi>heires of God,</hi> a ſecond ſtep higher, <hi>and ioynt heires with Chriſt,</hi> which is the higheſt ſteppe in the ladder of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> And this high prerogatiue of bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not onely a ſon, but an heire of God, &amp; a
<pb facs="tcp:17477:9"/> heire annexed with Chriſt, is elſe-where ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet forth: as where it is ſaid, <hi>We ſhal raigne with Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>2. Tim. 12. if we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him, wee ſhall alſo raigne with him:</hi> And where it is ſaid that we ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdome, as <hi>Luke 12.32. Feare not little flocke, for it is your fathers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to giue you the kingdome.</hi> And <hi>Mat. 25. Come ye bleſſed of my father, poſſeſſe the kingdome prepared for you from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundations of the Worlde:</hi> And to his Diſciples: <hi>Luc. 21.29. I appoynt you a kingdome as my Father appoynted me:</hi> and more generally to all: <hi>
                  <hi>Reue.</hi> 3.21. To him that ouercommeth, will I graunt to ſitte with me in my throne, euen as I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame and ſitte with my Father in his Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kingdome of Heauen is Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell-kinde Lande, where-in all the ſonnes are indifferently heires: yea, where the daughters haue like portion with the Sonnes, which both magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth highly the mercie of God, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth conſolation and comfort to him or her that is moſt baſe and deſpiſed in this worlde, when they conſider that the
<pb facs="tcp:17477:10"/> time wil come, when with the beſt they ſhall be fellow heires, and be ſet on a Throne together with them.</p>
            <p>And the more comfort it ſhall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto al, and make this our aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be the Sonnes of God, beyond all meaſure glorious, if wee conſider what maner of kingdome it is whereof we are made the vndoubted heires: It is the kingdome of Heauen (beloued) whereof God maketh all his ſonnes and daughters heires.<note place="margin">Luc. 12.32.</note> Our Sauiour Chriſt calleth it <hi>that kingdome,</hi> by excellencie, as a kingdome that ſurpaſſeth all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. S. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth it <hi>an inheritance, immortall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>inuiſible, vndefiled, neuer fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reſerued in heauen for vs:</hi> The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the Epiſtle vnto the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> calleth it <hi>a kingdome which cannot be ſhaken:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.28. Reuol. 21.19 21</note> The beautie and glorie of this kingdome is ſet foorth in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> vnder the name of the new Citie <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, where the foundations of the walls are ſaid, to bee garniſhed with pretious ſtones: The gates of the Citie to bee of Pearle, the ſtreetes of the Citie to be pure golde:</hi> expreſſing by theſe things which
<pb facs="tcp:17477:10"/> are of the greateſt price and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with vs, the beautie and the glorie of that kingdome which cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: The ioyes of this Kingdome are ſuch, as eye hath not ſéene, eare hath not heard, &amp; which the hart of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not able to conceiue,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>for we ſhal there receiue that crowne of glory,</hi> which ſhall neuer fade: Yea, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> calleth it, <hi>a far moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and an eternall waight of glorie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17</note> But of all this glory, were it farre more, if more could be, if one alone ſhould bee partaker, euen as the Philoſophers puts the caſe: or if he ſhould haue ſuch part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and fellowes (as this world for the moſt part in theſe daies affoordeth) as would be readie to deceiue, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſſeſſe him of all, or continually by their naughtines vexe him,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2 6</note> as the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> did the ſoule of righteous <hi>Lot</hi> and the daughters of <hi>Heth, Eſaus</hi> wifes,<note place="margin">Gen. 27.40</note> were a griefe of heart to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and to <hi>Rebeccah.</hi> If I ſay, it ſhould thus fall out with vs in the kingdome of heauen, the comfort thereof would be but litle, as mingled with ſo bitter a gall. But to increaſe our comfort in this reſpect, the Scripture
<pb facs="tcp:17477:11"/> ſheweth, that we ſhal not be there alone, or mixed with enuious, deceitfull, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe wicked wretches, but we ſhall haue <hi>the companie of innumerable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ieb. 12.22.</note> and of the ſpirits of iuſt and perfect men, and of Ieſus the mediatour of the New Teſtament: And as for Enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whoremongers, murtherers, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, lyers, and generally, all Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and euill diſpoſed perſons, they ſhall be ſhut out:<note place="margin">Reue. 21.27</note> 
               <hi>For none vncleane thing</hi> ſhall enter in at the gates of this citie to deminiſh the ioyes, or to pollute the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thereof. The exerciſe of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in this Citie, ſhall not bee Plough or Cart, or planting or grafting, or buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, and traffiquing by Sea or by Lande: it ſhall not be Hauking or Hunting, much leſſe dicing and carding, or any ſuch other like profane recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but it ſhall be a continuall ſinging of <hi>Allelu-iah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 19 4 Reue. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>prayſe and glorie and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thankes, and honour and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and might, bee vnto our God for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> No diſeaſes, either plague or peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhall be in this kingdome: no infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities either in bodie or in ſoule, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:17477:11"/> eclipſe the ioyes and the glorie thereof: <hi>For all teares ſhall there be wiped from all faces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.4</note> there ſhall be neither hunger or thirſt, or heate or colde, neither death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more. And what more can be added to expreſſe the height of that glorie, the vnſpeakable ioyes of that heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, whereof wee are heires apparant, that are the children of God? <hi>Non mihi ſi centum linguae ſint oraque centum ferrea vox, &amp;c.</hi> Not if I had an hundreth tongues, and an hundreth mouthes, and a voice ſo ſtrong as Iron, were I able to deſcipher in the perfection, the leaſt ioye and glorie of this celeſtiall inheritance. Oh that as <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſtanding on mount <hi>Piſgah,</hi> &amp; beholding the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut, 3.27</note> in the length and breadth thereof, or as the Apoſtles in mount <hi>Thabor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 17.2</note> ſéeing the brightneſſe and ſplendure of the Lorde Ieſus, when he was tranſfigured: or as S. <hi>Stephen, <hi>ſeeing the heauens open,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.56.</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helde the glorie of God, and Ieſus ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his right hand:</hi> Or as S. <hi>Paule,</hi> tranſported <hi>into the third heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſaw &amp; heard things ineffable.</hi> So it would pleaſe God to open the eies of our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:17477:12"/> and mindes, whereby we might haue, if not a perfect ſight, yet a glimpſe of this heauenly kingdome, that ſo wee might be throughly rauiſhed with a loue and a deſire thereof.</p>
            <p>If in our greateſt heauines, the newes of ſome great inheritance, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne vs, or of ſome ſmaller matter, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp our heads, and driueth all ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes from our hearts: ſhould not this newes which is brought vnto vs of ſuch a glorious kingdome in the middeſt of all our extremities and diſtreſſes, reliue our dead ſpirits, &amp; raiſe vp our heads that hang downe? What ſhould be the cauſe that we ſhould be ſo much addicted to the one, and ſo litle affected to the other? Is it becauſe the kingdome wee bring you tidings of, is an heauenly, and not an earthly kingdome? Doe wee not in the Fable, iuſtly condemne <hi>Aeſops</hi> Cocke of méere folly, for preferring a Barlie corne to a pretious Pearle? And is not <hi>Eſau</hi> iuſtly called by the authour of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.16</note> prophane: for that hee regarded a meſſe of Potage, more then the honour of his birth-right? And
<pb facs="tcp:17477:12"/> deſerue we not a greater condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if we prefer earth to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; a momentable pleaſure, to an eternall &amp; endles weight of glorie? Our kingdome, beloued, is not the leſſe to bee accepted, for that it is not earthly, but ten thouſand, thouſand times the more to be eſtéemed: for were our kingdome earthly, it ſhould be alſo tranſitorie: were our kingdome earthly, wee ſhould haue therein much ſorrow, care and griefe, mixed with ſmal felicity: were our kingdome earthly, wee might ſoone be diſpoſſeſſed thereof, either by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen warres, or by ſecrete conſpiracie. How ſuddenly was <hi>Zedechias</hi> diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of his kingdome, and caried captiue into <hi>Babilon,</hi> his eies thruſt out,<note place="margin">Iere. 52.11.</note> and him ſelfe thruſt into perpetuall priſon? Howe lamentably doth <hi>Moyſes</hi> (when he was made gouernour of that people) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, of the heauie burthen thereof,<note place="margin">Num. 11.15</note> and in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule, deſireth of the Lord that he would rather kill him, then to laye ſo heauie a loade vpon him? And for the tranſitorie eſtate of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as of al other earthly things, both ſmall and great, who ſéeth not that they
<pb facs="tcp:17477:13"/> can endure no longer then the earth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 3, 7</note> which, yet it belong, muſt <hi>by fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be conſumed with all the workes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> And yet who hath a leaſe of his life, or an aſſurance to hold his good til then? How many thouſands of our brethren within ſome fewe wéekes, by their ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die death, hath left vnto vs a preſident of this our fickle and vncertaine ſtate? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them leauing their ſubſtance not an inheritance for their babes, but a praye &amp; a ſpoyle to ſtrangers, to waſte and to deuoure.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed therefore be God the Father of our Lord Ieſus, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his aboundant mercie, hath begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs to a liuely hope, by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt from the dead, To an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,</hi> not mortal, <hi>but immortall, inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, vndeſiled, neuer fading, reſerued</hi> not on earth, but <hi>in heauen for vs, Which are kept by the power of God thorow faith vnto ſaluation, which is prepated to bee ſhewed in the laſt time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we haue ſéene how euery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of waye, this our heauenly enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance excelleth all earthly kingdomes, and thereby, to how great a dignitie it is
<pb facs="tcp:17477:13"/> that we are exalted vnto, in that we are made the ſonnes of God, and heires of that euerlaſting kingdome of glorie.</p>
            <p>And the conſideration hereof mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth great comfort vnto vs, in regards of our deare friends deceaſed: for that we know, that ſo many of them as dyed in the faith of Chriſt, they haue receiued the poſſeſſion of this kingdome, enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized with a more glorious fréedome, then all the fréedomes of the world, and haue gotten the victorie of Satan, ſinne and Hell,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.16.</note> and death no longer to holde their bodies, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trumpet ſhal ſound: Ariſe ye dead, and come into iudgement. Why therefore ſhould we bewaile them who from miſerie are gone vnto glorie, who from pouertie are aſcended vp into a throne of maieſtie: who from continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all labour and toyle, are remooued into a place of perpetuall reſt and quietneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> according vnto that voice that ſaide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iohn: <hi>Write,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 14.13</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ourſelues, whom God in mercie hath yet paſſed by, and granted to liue to
<pb facs="tcp:17477:14"/> ſée this day, we may hereby receiue this comfort, that we being his children this viſitation, if it ſhall pleaſe him to laye it vpon vs, as he hath done vpon many of our brethren better then wee, ſhall not tende vnto our deſtruction, but to the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of vs ſeaſon and liuerie as it were, and full poſſeſſion of this our heauenly inheritance.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay vnto me, Is there then no note of God his diſpleaſure and anger in this ſickneſſe? Is it not an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie iudgement of God, which our ſinnes haue drawne downe vpon vs? Yes veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, manifeſt notes of God his iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued wrath and fearefull iudgements appeareth in this viſitation: and that as to the bad, ſo to the good: as to them that are dead, ſo to vs that remaine aliue.</p>
            <p>A feareful iudgement it is to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and reprobate, if there be any ſuch that haue departed: who, as they liued not in the feare, ſo died, not in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God. For this ſudden cutting them off, ſheweth that their ſinnes were ripe and growne to a full height, and that they are now gathered as it were in
<pb facs="tcp:17477:14"/> bundles to be throwne into hell fyer.</p>
            <p>A fearefull iudgement alſo it is, euen to God his owne children that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: the guilt and eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of whoſe ſinnes, though they bee forgiuen in Chriſt, and they receiued to mercie through him: yet God by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie and ſharpe, though tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affliction, would ſhew that hee was highly diſpleaſed, both with them and with vs for our ſinnes, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath taken them away, the moſt of them in the prime and middeſt of their daies, from further enioying the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of long life, which alſo he promiſeth vnto them that truely doe loue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him.</p>
            <p>A fearefull iudgement it is vpon vs that are remaining: for what is this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding, in ſo vncomfortable a maner, of the huſband from the wife, of the wife from the huſband, of parents from their children, &amp; children from their parents, of friend from friend, and acquaintance from acquaintance? but as it were a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing and deuiding of the ſame bodie, into diuerſe pieces: when the huſband
<pb facs="tcp:17477:15"/> dieth, the wife hath loſt her head, when the wife dieth, the huſband hath loſt his right hand: When the parents die, the children haue loſt the eye, to guide them: when the children die, the parents haue loſt the ſight that ſhould comfort them: when a brother dieth, the brother hath loſt parte of his owne fleſh and bones: when a friend dieth, his friend hath loſt (as the Philoſopher calleth him) <hi>alter i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> another himſelfe: Beſides, the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities which befal the common ſtates as not onely whole families to be deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, but Cities and Townes to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled: the number of poore Widowes and Orphanes to bee encreaſed, trades and occupations to be ceaſed, yea, tillage it ſelfe to be decaied, whereby ſore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine is threatned. It paſſeth my reach, beloued, to ſounde the depth of God his fearefull iudgement in this behalfe: for this breach made vpon ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the people, is as it were a breach made in the wall of a citie, whereby the enemie entreth and poſſeſſeth the ſame.</p>
            <p>What then remaineth, but that wee turne from our ſinnes, that God may
<pb facs="tcp:17477:15"/> turne from his wrathfull indignation? A naturall Father, though hee loue his ſonne well, wil not leaue chaſtiſing him till hee hath left offending: and if in the time of his chaſtiſement, hee ſheweth himſelfe ſtubborne, and to haue an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate minde to continue in his naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, he wil lay on more heauie ſtripes, and his ſoule ſhall not ſpare for his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring: we haue a moſt tender and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, gratious and abounding in all compaſſion towardes vs, we haue offended him in moſt grieuous &amp; feareful maner. It grieueth my hart, O <hi>London,</hi> to thinke vpon, much more to rehearſe the horrible ſinnes committed in thée: for, conſider whether as againſt <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> God may not complaine thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée? <hi>In thee they haue deſpiſed Father and Mother:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 22.7</note> 
               <hi>In thee they haue op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the ſtranger: In thee they haue vexed the fatherleſſe and the Widdow: Thou haſt deſpiſed mine holy things, and polluted my Sabboth. In thee are men to carie tales to ſhead bloud: In thee are they that eate vpon the Mountaines, as</hi> Popiſh recuſants: <hi>In the middeſt of thee
<pb facs="tcp:17477:16"/> they commit abhominations: as inceſt, and adulterie: In thee are they that take gifts to ſhed bloud.</hi> Thou haſt taken the vſurie and the increaſe, and thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded thy neighbour by extortion. And would to God that this bitter complaint were all, and that it might be onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée; But againſt thée O <hi>England</hi> in generall, doth God thus complaine, with a Bill containing the ſame, and more &amp; more grieuous accuſations both againſt Courte and Countrie, againſt Church and common weale: as of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, of drunkennes, of pride &amp; coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, of horrible Witchcraft &amp; ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of immeaſurable briberie: of buying &amp; ſelling offices in the common weale: of buying &amp; ſelling dignities in the Church: of inſatiable auarice &amp; ambition in both: in the one, of heaping offices to offices, in the other, of laying benefices to benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in neither a care or conſcience to performe the dutie to the common good, but to their owne gaine and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And herein, God appealeth to the conſciences of you all, that he ſlandereth not the ſtate: neither doeth this bill of
<pb facs="tcp:17477:16"/> complaint tend to the diſparagement of our late bleſſed Soueraigne deceaſed, in whoſe times theſe abhominations ſpra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and grew vp, and increaſed to ſuch an height. For, be it farre from me, that I ſhould let a ſillable fall to the diſhonour of her being dead whom (as dutie bound with my ſoule) I honoured being aliue. The like enormities to theſe, fell out in the raigne of good and vertuous kings: Yea, in their raigne who were moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned of al the reſt: as of <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and <hi>Joſias,</hi> as appeareth by the complaint of the Prophets, who prophecied in their daies. It was in the daies of <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> that <hi>Eſaiah</hi> the Prophet thus complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.<note place="margin">Eſa. 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>In that daye did the Lorde God of Hoſtes, call vnto weeping and mourning, &amp; to baldneſſe, and to a girding of Sacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and beholde, ioy and gladneſſe, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Sheepe &amp; ſlaying of Oxen, eating &amp; drinking, to morrow we ſhall die.</hi> It was in the time of <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> when <hi>Micah</hi> the Prophet thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth. <hi>cap. 7. ver. 2.4 The good man is periſhed out of the earth and there is none righteous among men, the beſt of them is as a bryer, and the
<pb facs="tcp:17477:17"/> moſt righteous, ſharper then a thorne hedge.</hi> It was in the time of <hi>Joſiah, Jere. <hi>cap, 3. verſ. 6. &amp; 10.</hi>
               </hi> That God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Ieremie</hi> thus to vp-braide <hi>Iudah. The rebellious Iſrael hath iuſtifyed her ſelfe more then the rebellious Iudah, for they haue not returned vnto me with all their hart, but fainedly ſaith the Lord:</hi> and therefore he biddeth him. <hi>Iere. 5.1.3.4.5 &amp;c.</hi> To <hi>runne to and fro in the ſtreetes of Ieruſalem, and to aske and to enquire if he could finde a man that executeth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and iudgement, and ſeeketh the truth, &amp; he would ſpare it.</hi> And he got him to the poore men, &amp; alas they were then, as for the moſt part they are now, <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and fooliſh, they knew not the waye of the Lord nor the iudgement of their God.</hi> He went <hi>to the great men,</hi> and they were ſuch, as for the moſt part they are nowe, they made great profeſſion, but they alſo <hi>had</hi> altogether <hi>broke the yoke, &amp; burſt the bands,</hi> that is, they would not be ordered by the Law of God. It was in the time of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that <hi>Zephaniah</hi> the Prophet complaineth thus,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12</note> That there were <hi>men in Ieruſalem frozen in their
<pb facs="tcp:17477:17"/> dregs, &amp; ſay in their hearts, the Lord will neither do good nor euill:</hi> nay thus more generally in the <hi>2. cap. 1. 2, Woe be to the polluted, to the robbing Citie, ſhe heard not the voice, ſhee receiued not correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe truſted not in the Lord, ſhe drewe not neere to her God.</hi> And particularly, as it were by name, in the <hi>3.</hi> verſe. <hi>Her Princes within her are as Lyons, her Iudges as Wolues in the Euening, which leaue not the bones to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning: her Prophets are light and wicked perſons, her Prieſts haue polluted the Sanctuarie; and wreſted the Law.</hi> And yet all theſe corruptions whereof they thus bitterly complaine, and for which they were not accuſed for ſlandring of the ſtate, were no ſtayne to their memoriall. For that they laboured and endeuoured to their vtmoſt, to haue reformed them, as their hiſtories ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently doe ſhewe, and therefore are Chronicled to haue done vprightly in the ſight of the Lord. In like manner, who is ignorant of the godly zeale of Quéene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for the true worſhip and ſeruice of God for ſuppreſſing of vice, both in Church &amp; common weale,
<pb facs="tcp:17477:18"/> and maintenance of vertue? ſo that her Throne ſhee left and reſigned to Noble King <hi>IAMES,</hi> vnſtained of theſe abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: the guilt thereof to cleaue to them and their poſteritie, who were the cauſers of them. But as <hi>Ioab</hi> and the ſonnes of <hi>Zeruiah</hi> were to hard for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi> and <hi>Sebna</hi> was a Patron of vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines vnder <hi>Ezechias,</hi> and the Princes, the Iudges, the Prophets, the Prieſtes corrupt vnder <hi>Ioſiah:</hi> and yet none of theſe good Kings bore the blame of their euill counſellours:<note place="margin">Sam. 3.39.</note> So it is nothing to the impeachme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the honour of Quéene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but rather renowneth her much, that ſhe continued her courſe, and to the laſt yéere encreaſed her zeale,<note place="margin">Eſa. 22, 15</note> which could be quenched neither by any <hi>Ioab,</hi> nor by al the ſonnes of <hi>Zeruiah,</hi> nor by any <hi>Sebnah,</hi> nor by any ambitious Prince, or corrupt Iudge, or flattering Prophet or Prelate, nor by that maine ſea of iniquitie, which in her time ſo out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageouſlie burſt foorth: But it tendeth much to the condemnation of this Citie and our Lande, that hauing ſo godly a Gouerneſſe, wee regarded not her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,
<pb facs="tcp:17477:18"/> but neglected her Lawes and liued after our own wils and pleaſures, in all the abhominations before rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>And nowe, what could our gratious God and heauenly Father do leſſe, then, firſt taking her to his mercie (whom we were vnworthie longer to haue) to take the rodde into his owne hand, to beat vs for our ſinnes, to correct vs for our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, &amp; to prooue, if his owne chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would effect our amendment? Let vs therefore euerie one of vs, in the feare of God, who ſtand in awe of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, turne from his owne euil waies, and from the wickedneſſe that is in his handes, as did the <hi>Niniuites.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iona, 3, 10.</note> Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man <hi>ceaſe to do euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa, 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>and learne to do well:</hi> Let euery man <hi>plough vp his fallow ground, &amp; ſowe no more among thornes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 4, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Let euery man caſt away the abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his eies</hi> and of his heart: yea,<note place="margin">Eze, 20.7</note> let vs all turne to the Lorde with faſting, wéeping and mourning,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>renting our harts and not our garments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh let it be far from vs, that this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint that the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> taketh
<pb facs="tcp:17477:19"/> vp againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſhould be taken vp againſt vs. <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſtricken them, but they haue not ſorrowed, thou haſt conſumed them, but they haue refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed correction, they haue made their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces harder then a ſtone, and haue refuſed to returne.</hi> For if notwithſtanding theſe iudgements of God, we continue ſtill in thoſe ſins which haue thus ſore kindled his wrath, if in this day of our viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherein the Lorde calleth to wéeping &amp; mourning, to ſackcloth &amp; aſhes, we fal to eating &amp; drinking, that is, to our wonted gluttonie &amp; drunkennes, &amp; other abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: Let vs aſſure our ſelues that the wrath of God will ſtill burne, and his arme be ſtretched out ſtill, vntil hee hath laide our land waſte, and this Citie without an inhabitant.</p>
            <p>As therefore it ſtandeth euery man vpon to mend one, ſo to you right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, and your worſhipful aſſiſtants, it belongeth to reforme them that will not reforme themſelues, and betimes to cut off all the workers of iniquitie from the Citie of the Lord. And for a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall redreſſe of all abuſes and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:17477:19"/> both in our Church and common weale: we ought earneſtly and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to pray vnto almightie God, to put into the heart of our moſt Noble and bleſſed Soueraigne, the kings Maieſtie, both conſtantly to withſtand all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, of corrupt mindes, and to haſten as he hath moſt zealouſlie begun the full amendment of whatſoeuer is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe: euen to the making of a couenant betwixt God and his people, that they ſhall ſéeke the Lorde, and that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will not ſéeke the Lord God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, that he be ſlaine, whether hee bee great or ſmall, man or woman, as did <hi>Aſa</hi> King of <hi>Iudah.</hi> For God will not be reconciled vnto vs,<note place="margin">2. Cro. 15.12</note> vntill we yéelde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: For hee is our Father, and wée are his Children, for our ſinnes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeth he thus ſmite vs: And as the Father ceaſeth not his puniſhing hand ſo long as his Sonne continueth obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: No more, now he hath begun, wil hee giue ouer, vntill wee humble our ſelues vnfaynedly before him: For ſince our ſinnes haue in this ſort incenſed his wrath as we muſt néeds confes, though
<pb facs="tcp:17477:20"/> his mercie vnto vs that are his children appeareth herein that the finall end of this viſitation, tendeth to the perfecting thorow his mercie, which triumpheth ouer his iuſtice of our eternall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Iam. 2</note> yet his angrie countenance ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe no leſſe vnto vs in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof, then the anger of a diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Father appeareth in his face, when hee chaſtizeth his diſobedient childe (whom he loueth) for his good.</p>
            <p>And thus haue I ſhewed vnto you, right Honorable and beloued, how in this viſitation, wee may receiue both ſingular comfort ouer them that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and for our ſelues who yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to be diſpoſed of by his good will and pleaſure, and alſo perceiue God his iuſt diſpleaſure and anger againſt vs for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>It remaineth, that we procéede in the purſuit of God his mercie to vs, which we haue ſhewed to haue bene excéeding great, in making vs to be his Sonnes: and ſhal now ſhew to be excéeding grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in conſidering of the originall and fountaine from whence this ſo vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:17477:20"/> a mercie floweth vnto vs. For the verie original ſpring, is the loue of God: for ſo our Apoſtle affirmeth: <hi>Behold what loue the Father hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs:</hi> Which alſo our Sauiour Chriſt confirmeth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>So God loued the Worlde,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.16.</note> that hee gaue his onely begotten Sonne, &amp;c.</hi> and that not an ordinarie, but an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie loue, for ſo the wordes impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and which the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which our Apoſtle here vſeth alſo ſignifyeth. For this word ſignifyeth, what maner: with an admiration: ſo that the text is to be read: thus, <hi>behold what maner of loue the Father hath giuen vs,</hi> For ſo is this word alſo vſed. <hi>Mar. 13.1. What maner of ſtones, and what maner of building,</hi> as if they ſhould ſay not ordinarie, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie ſtones, not ordinarie, but extraordinarie buildings are here. So in the <hi>8.</hi> of <hi>Matt. 27.</hi> after our Sauiour had ſtilled the raging of the Sea, the men marueiled ſaying: <hi>What maner of man is this:</hi> as if they ſhould ſay what rare and ſingular man? Such a loue then is the loue of God, whereby hee hath choſen vs to be his children, as is
<pb facs="tcp:17477:21"/> paſt vnderſtanding, as is extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as is a wonder of wonders: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here ſet forth by two words of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derment. <hi>Beholde, what maner?</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, you ſhall the better beholde and conſider how admirable and wonderful a loue it is wherewith God hath loued vs? If ye obſerue firſt on whom he hath-beſtowed it: Secondly, in what ſort hee hath beſtowed it: And thirdly, by what perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath effected it. He hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it vpon <hi>vs,</hi> and hee hath beſtowed it <hi>gratis</hi> in maner of a gift, and he hath ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected it, by his owne onely Sonne our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt whom he gaue vnto death for vs.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, it is ſaid that he gath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his loue to <hi>vs:</hi> For our ſelues, if wee had bene the friendes of God, or had in any wiſe deſerued any ſmall matter at his hand, the loue had not bene ſo great, as louing <hi>vs</hi> that had loued him, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that our Sauiour ſaith of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>loue one towards another. If yee loue them that loue you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.46</note> 
               <hi>what rewarde ſhall ye haue? doe not alſo the verie Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanes</hi> and moſt notorious ſinners <hi>thus?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17477:21"/> The Iewes tolde our Sauiour, that the <hi>Centurion</hi> was worthie for his deſerts towarde their Nation, that hee ſhould heale his ſeruant: which, had it ben true, the benefite beſtowed vpon him,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.4,</note> had not bene ſo great: But the <hi>Centurion</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth himſelfe vnworthie, not pleading any deſert: for there is no ſuch matter indéede of deſert on our part to God-warde: for we were the vtter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God, and this enmitie was wrought betwixt God and vs, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our ſins. For as God by reaſon of our ſin, was at enmity with vs,<note place="margin">Ephe, 2.3.</note> in which reſpect, we are called <hi>the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods wrath:</hi> ſo we were at vtter variance or defyance with him,<note place="margin">Iob. 2, 9.</note> curſing him to the face, as <hi>Iob</hi> his wife did councell him: which alſo the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 8.7,</hi> teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, when as he ſayeth: <hi>The wiſdome of the fleſh is an vtter enemie to God, for it is not a ſubiect,</hi> therefore a rebell <hi>to the Law of God,</hi> neither otherwiſe can be.</p>
            <p>In that therefore God through Ieſus Chriſt, yéelded on his part to loue vs, we continuing our diſobedience and hatred towards him: how great muſt
<pb facs="tcp:17477:22"/> that his loue be? For if the partie wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall yéelde vnto him that doeth the wrong, and ſhall ſéeke his good will, and his good, what rare loue do we account it? yea, ſo rare, as is ſeldome (the more is the pittie) to be ſéene among vs.</p>
            <p>This loue of God therefore in this poynt, is a rare loue, and excéeding ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, in that hee loued vs, being his enemies, and ſought after vs, when wee ſought not after him, according to that he ſaieth by the Prophet <hi>Eſay 65.1. <hi>I haue offred my ſelfe to be found of them that asked not:</hi>
               </hi> For ſo the verbe Paſſiue there vſed, is to bee tranſlated. Like as the Apoſtle <hi>Ro. 10.20.</hi> rendreth it. <hi>I haue bene made manifeſt:</hi> For otherwiſe the ſence of the firſt comma in that ſwéete ſentence, cannot be perceiued. <hi>I offered my ſelfe</hi> (ſaieth God) <hi>to bee founde of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that asked not I was found of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſought mee not. I ſaide behold mee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde me, to a Nation that called not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my name:</hi> And as by the miniſterie of his Prophets in former time, ſo by our Miniſterie now, doeth he ſtill ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vs, that continue ſtill our enmitie to
<pb facs="tcp:17477:22"/> him: For wee are <hi>the embaſſadours,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>2. Corinth. 5.20.</hi> for Chriſt, as though God did beſéech you thorow vs, we pray you in Chriſt ſtead, that ye bee reconciled vnto God: The greatneſſe therfore of God his loue towards vs in this behalfe, doeth the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> highly, as it deſerueth renowne: <hi>Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> ſaieth he <hi>for a righteous man, one can ſcarcely be found that will die: but for a good man it may bee one dare die: but God magnifieth his mercie vnto vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5,</note> 
               <hi>that when we were his enemies, Chriſt dyed for vs.</hi> And againe, <hi>when wee were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, we were reconciled vnto him by the death of his Sonne.</hi> This he proſecuteth in many words in the <hi>2. Epheſ.</hi> but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the <hi>4. verſe</hi> in theſe words. <hi>But God which is rich in mercie thorow his great loue, wherewith he loued vs, euen when we were dead in ſinnes,</hi> that is, his mortall enemies, <hi>he quickned vs toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt.</hi> Thus wee ſée, how in this reſpect this holy Apoſtle magnifyeth the greatneſſe of Gods loue and grace,<note place="margin">Ephe, 2, 7.</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it <hi>the exceeding riches of his grace:</hi> for that he loued vs, when we were his
<pb facs="tcp:17477:23"/> enemies. And therefore doe wee not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte them worthily enemies to the grace of God, who doe obſcure or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther denie this his great grace, <hi>operibus praeuiſis,</hi> by workes fore-ſéene: and I know not what the Lord Ieſus himſelf ſaw no ſuch workes fore-ſéene when he taught vs to ſay: <hi>we are vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,</hi> we haue done but that which was our dutie to doe. This our Apoſtle ſawe no ſuch fore-ſéene workes, and there fore he renowneth this loue of GOD,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe hee loued vs firſt, ſaying in the <hi>4. chap. 10. Herein is loue, not that we lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God, but that hee loued vs firſt:</hi> and againe, in the <hi>19. verſe: We loue him, for he loued vs firſt.</hi> This doctrine then teacheth vs, that by grace we are ſaued, and therfore not by works alone, nor by grace and workes together: for workes and grace cannot goe together in the worke of iuſtifycation, for ſo the Apoſtle reaſoneth. <hi>If it be of grace, it is no more of works, or elſe were grace no more grace: but if it be of workes, it is no more grace, or elſe were worke no more worke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug, de fide et o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Cap. 14</note> Well therefore ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtne,</hi> concerning
<pb facs="tcp:17477:23"/> good workes: <hi>Sequutur iuſtifica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caedunt iuſtificandum:</hi> they follow him that is iuſtifyed, they goe not before him that is to be iuſtifyed. For by the way, this is to be noted, that though workes ſaue vs not, yet we are the workmanſhip of God, created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good works, for to glorifie him that ſaued vs, according as <hi>Zacharias</hi> ſayth in his ſong: <hi>Wee are deliuered from the hands of our enemies, that wee might ſerue him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, all the dayes of our life in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe before him. And the grace of God,</hi> ſaieth the Apoſtle vnto <hi>Titus, that bringeth ſaluation vnto all men:</hi> hath appeared and teacheth vs, that we ſhould denie vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts: and that wee ſhould liue ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent world. And our Apoſtle mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this to be our dutie, namely, to purge our ſelues, wherof, if time would permit, to come to the handling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part, which is, the ſecond parte of our text, we would by the grace of God more largely ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this doctrine teacheth vs, to loue one another: which leſſon, this
<pb facs="tcp:17477:24"/> our Apoſtle inferreth vpon the loue of God,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.9.</note> in the <hi>11. verſe</hi> of this Chapter: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, if God ſo loued vs, wee ought alſo to loue one another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.18</note> So S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayeth, <hi>We are taught of God,</hi> that is, by the example of God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.16.</note> to loue one another, and that not in worde and in tongue, giuing onely faire words: Goe in peace, be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, bee warmed, and giue naught, and thinke naught, <hi>but in deede and in truth,</hi> that is, wee ought to manifeſt our loue vnto all, by dealing faithfully and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with all men, and to them that are in want, by miniſtring vnto their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For hereby is loue proued, as by a touch-ſtone <hi>If any man hath this worlds goods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.1</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeth his brother want, and ſhutteth vp his compaſsion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him?</hi> as if hee ſhould ſaye, Such a man neither loueth God nor man: And beloued, now is the time if euer you will, that you muſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt your loue to God by tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on them that are in néede. I néed not to vtter vnto you the great miſerie, of the poore of this Citie, and of the Suburbs thereof: the want of the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb facs="tcp:17477:24"/> and of the fatherleſſe, and of the poore man of occupation, who in this time wanteth woorke, and therefore wanteth foode for him and his familie. Their crie is come before you out of this place, and you haue moſt honorably and charitably conſidered of it. I beſéech you in the tender bowels of the Lord Ieſus, conſider of it ſtill, for the ſickneſſe thus ſtill (though not in ſo great meaſure, the Lord be euer praiſed for it) continuing, &amp; the Winter ſo hard approching, and none or litle worke, as they ſay, ſtirring, the number of the poore, &amp; their neceſſity, do encreaſe daily: your liberality there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt alſo encreaſe, Rather then the poore ſhould want, make a banke for the poore, it would be the moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble banke that euer was made, and moſt profitable for the aduenturers. Let him that hath twentie thouſand pound, caſt in two thouſande: Let him that hath ten thouſand pound, caſt in a thouſand: Let him that hath a thouſand, caſt in a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, let him that hath an hundreth, caſt in ten. I know I ſhall be cenſured by many to ſpeake like a foole, but I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:17477:25"/> not their cenſure. For this propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not like to his that ſaide, <hi>let him that hath two coates, giue one to him that hath none, and let him that hath meate do likewiſe:</hi> nor like vnto his that ſaid, <hi>Halfe of my goods I giue to the poore:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 3.11</note> Nor like vnto his that ſaid, <hi>Sell all that thou haſt and giue to the poore:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 19.8 Mat. 19.21</note> Nor like to theirs <hi>that ſold their houſes and poſſeſsions, and brought the price to bee diſtributed to them that wanted:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.34 Luc. 21.2</note> Nor like hers, that <hi>hauing but two mites,</hi> caſt them into this banke, <hi>being all the liuing ſhe had,</hi> being content to worke for more. Yet as the meaning of theſe ſayings, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples is not to ſet any iuſt rate, but to ſhew that charitie muſt ouer-flowe in time of common neceſſitie: ſo my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not, to preſcribe vnto your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, either a iuſt proportion, or a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of taxing: but to ſhew how farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth in liberalitie, euerie one without compulſion, of his owne willing and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie minde (for <hi>Hilarem da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orem dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git dominus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor 9.7</note> The Lord loueth a chéereful giuer) ought to excéede, to relieue the great miſerie of them that are in want.
<pb facs="tcp:17477:25"/> And this to doe in regard of that loue wherewith God haue loued vs: for hee loued vs before wee loued him: he loued vs, when wee were his enemies: and therefore his example not onely teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to loue ſuch as are our friendes, which ſtand in néede, or to loue them, who, as they haue done vs no good, ſo they haue done vs no hurt, but euen them that haue wronged vs, we ought to helpe. Farre therefore ought theſe, (though vſual, yet vnchriſtian ſpéeches) be from vs: ſhall I loue him that hates me? ſhal I do him good that hath wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me? Alas, beloued, God ſtood not vpon theſe tearmes with vs: he loued vs when we were his enemies, when wee blaſpheamed him,<note place="margin">Math. 5.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; ſhal not we by his example, who alſo doeth good to the <hi>iuſt and the vniuſt, cauſing his ſunne to ſhine, &amp; his raine to fall on them</hi> indifferently, ſhall not wee (I ſaye) by his example, learne to bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that curſe vs,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> to pray for them that perſecute vs, to doe good to them that wrong vs?</p>
            <p>Let vs not deceiue our ſelues in boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that wee are the children of God:
<pb facs="tcp:17477:26"/> for vnleſſe this affection in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be in vs, we are no ſonnes of God, nor God any Father of ours.</p>
            <p>But to procéede in magnifying fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this loue of God: the Apoſtle affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that this loue which is beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, is in maner of a gift, gratis: For he hath giuen it vs. Some men deſerue loue for ſome good turnes or deſerts that they haue done, and ſo make him to bee a friend, which before was an enemie: as <hi>Iacob</hi> won <hi>Eſau:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 32.20,</note> But who hath giuen to the Lord firſt, and he ſhall be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed.<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.13. Rom. 11.35</note> So the Lord demandeth by his Prophet, and by his Apoſtle, and who euer haue ſtood forth, &amp; a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwerd to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, I haue giuen: Not <hi>Abraham,</hi> for he acknowledgeth himſelfe to bee <hi>duſt and aſhes.</hi> Not <hi>Dauid,</hi> for he prayeth: <hi>Enter not into iudgement with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 18 27. Pſal. 143. Iob. 28, 20.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord.</hi> Not <hi>Iob,</hi> for he confeſſeth: <hi>If hee ſhould iuſtifie himſelfe, his owne mouth would condemne him.</hi> God hath not ſet his loue to ſale vnto vs: for if he had, whereby ſhould or could we haue procured it? ſhould we haue giuen him a <hi>thouſand Rammes</hi> (to vſe the wordes of
<pb facs="tcp:17477:26"/> the Prophet <hi>Micah) or ten thouſand ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of oyle:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould wee haue offered him the fruit of the bodie for the ſinnes of our ſoule?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.10.</note> none of all theſe earthly things are ours, they are all his: ſo he teſtifyeth. <hi>All the beaſts of the field are mine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo are the cattle vpon a thouſand hilles: And as the ſoule of the fathers is mine,</hi> ſayeth the Lorde, <hi>ſo is the ſoule of the ſonnes.</hi> And more generally: <hi>The earth is the Lords, and all the fulneſſe thereof, the rounde worlde, and all that dwell therein.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> But were theſe earthly things all ours, yet were they all too baſe to buy the leaſt parcell of God his heauenly grace and loue towards vs. For what compariſon is there betwixt earthly things and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things? betwixt things temporall and tranſitorie, and things ſpiritual, and eternall?</p>
            <p>The ſtring whereupon many, and eſpecially the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doeth harpe in this reſpect, is our righteouſnes: but what our righteouſnes is, Yea al our righteouſneſſes are (the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> telleth vs,<note place="margin">Eſa. 64 6.</note> when hee ſaith they are) <hi>as a ſtained cloth, which lotheth the eyes of
<pb facs="tcp:17477:27"/> them that beholde,</hi> ſo that with diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and deteſtation they turne from it. Our righteouſneſſe therefore in it ſelfe conſidered without the merit of Chriſt, by whom they are accepted, as fruits of our faith, they are too much ſtained, and therefore too baſe to procure the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant riches of the loue of God. And this we muſt néedes of our ſelues confeſſe, if we be not caried away with too great a ſelfe-loue, &amp; weening of our ſelues: for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen our conſcience which is a thouſand, witneſſes, witneſſeth againſt vs, the manifold corruptions which cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the beſt and moſt holy worke that we doe.</p>
            <p>The trueth therefore of this doctrine remayneth inuinſible, and néedeth no further teſtimonie of any man, that, that eternall loue of God, wherewith hee hath ſo loued vs, as to make vs his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and heires, is, of his frée gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed and giuen vnto vs, according as our Apoſtle here ſayth, <hi>Behold what loue the father hath giuen vnto vs, that wee ſhould be called the Sonnes of God:</hi> and according to that the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>Gal.
<pb facs="tcp:17477:27"/> 3.22. The promiſe by the faith of Chriſt Ieſus, is giuen to them that beleeue:</hi> for this one worde <hi>giuen,</hi> ſo often repeated by the Apoſtle, if there were no further argument to prooue the fréenes of God his loue and grace towardes vs, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſtoppe all mouthes, that open themſelues to the derogation thereof. But yet further to remooue all opinion and conceit of our owne worthineſſe, and to ſet foorth the loue of GOD, to bee beyond all meaſure, GOD to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the vtmoſt tittle of his iuſtice, and to cancell all obligations and hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings againſt vs for our ſinnes, finding nothing in vs, whereby to ſaue vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as one well confeſſeth to him: <hi>Nihil inuenis vnde ſalues, &amp; multum inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, vnde damnes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt de verbis Apoſt ſer. 16.</note> thou findeſt nothing for which thou maieſt ſaue vs, but thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt much, for which thou maiſt damne vs. God I ſaie, ſent his onely Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, who is with the Father, and the holy ſpirit, <hi>God bleſſed for euer,</hi> to take on him our nature,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.5</note> and therein to ſatiſfie the whole ſeueritie of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and to pay the vtmoſt farthing of
<pb facs="tcp:17477:28"/> our debt. The greatneſſe of the loue of God in this behalfe, doeth our Sauiour himſelfe expreſſe, as we haue ſhewed, in ſaying:<note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>God ſo loued the world, that hee gaue his only begotten ſonne vnto death, that whoſoeuer ſhould beleeue on him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi> This alſo doeth our Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, in the fourth Chapter verſe <hi>10. Herein is loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>not that wee loued God, but that hee loued vs, and ſent his onely begotten ſonne, to be a reconciliation for our ſinnes:</hi> Where the loue of God is ſet in the firſt place, for the cauſe effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and principall, <hi>his ſonne</hi> ſent for the cauſe materiall, and to be a reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for our ſinnes: for a cauſe finall, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing required of vs, but that we beléeue in him, and loue one another for him, as he hath loued vs. If the conſideration hereof were throughly layed to hart, it would quickly remooue all proud opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our owne merit, which is thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by including the merit of Chriſt, as alone the ſufficient ſacrifice propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie for our ſinnes: and it would ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vs vp with an admiration of the
<pb facs="tcp:17477:28"/> excéeding loue of God toward vs:<note place="margin">Epe, 318.</note> 
               <hi>The height, the depth, the length, the breadth whereof is incomprehenſible,</hi> and make vs aſhamed of our owne corruption: Gold and ſiluer, and pretious ſtones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of no valew: all the Sacrifices and ceremonies of the old Law, being of no worth: his bleſſed and glorious Angels being inſufficient to effect our ranſome, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſo loued: he ſpared not his owne onely ſonne, who was in his boſome more deare vnto him, than the ſignet of his owne right hande, who willingly ſaid alſo; <hi>Loe I come,</hi> and gaue him to the death, by his death to redéeme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.6, 7 Heb. 10, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſwéet ſaying of S. <hi>Peter, We were not redeemed by ſiluer or gold,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18.19</note> or by any other corruptible things, but by the pretious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as of a Lambe immaculate, and without ſpot. And wee, in the meane while wretched men and women, ſtraine at euery curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and thinke euery thing too much we do in loue towards our brethren, whom wee ſhould not onely loue by ſupplying their wants in the expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our goods, as before we haue ſhewed, but alſo loue, by
<pb facs="tcp:17477:29"/> laying downe our liues for them, by the expence of our bloud, if néede ſo require: as our Apoſtle by this example of our bleſſed Sauiour teacheth vs, ſaying: <hi>here in is loue,</hi> that hee laide downe his life for vs: wee ought therefore to laye downe our liues for the brethren. <hi>1. Ioh. 3.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remayneth in this clauſe, yet one worde that further amplifyeth this loue of God in the greatnes thereof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: For beſides that, it hath pleaſed him to make vs, euen vs that were his enemies to be his ſonnes, to be his heires and ioynt heires with his owne natural ſonne: of ſuch an inheritance, that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, and that of his méere loue by gift, not deſerued by vs, but purchaſed for vs, by the pretious death and paſſion of our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, he vouchſafeth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> further aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our faith herein, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of our ſoules to cal himſelf our father, <hi>for adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs in his welbeloued Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.7</note> as his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Son by nature, is not aſhamed (as the authour of the Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> wel obſerueth to cal vs, euen vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17477:29"/> were adopted (from a thing of naught) his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſaying,<note place="margin">Hebr. 2, 16.</note> 
               <hi>I wil declare thy name vnto my brethren:</hi> ſo God his Father, the Father by excellencie, diſdaineth not to cal himſelfe our Father, ſaying:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.18</note> I wil <hi>bee your Father, and ye ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters.</hi> The worde <hi>Father</hi> is a ſwéet worde, and ſerueth to be obſerued for many vſes. Firſt, it confirmeth al the former doctrine of GOD his louing vs fréely: for as the childe receiueth nothing but from his Father, and his Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth all things vpon him fréely, in regard onely, that he is his Father, the childe deſeruing not the leaſt iotte of his loue: So God being our Father, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that we receiue all from him, our being, our lyuing, our mouing,<note place="margin">Act, 17, 28</note> benefites Temporall, bleſſings Spirituall, &amp; that of his owne méere loue, becauſe he is our Father without any deſert or merit of ours.</p>
            <p>Secondly it expreſſeth more ſenſibly the tender mercie and compaſſion of our good God vnto vs: for thereby wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that he tendreth vs as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to that of the Prophet:
<pb facs="tcp:17477:30"/> 
               <hi>Like as a father pittieth his owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 103, 13</note> 
               <hi>euen ſo the Lord hath compaſsion on them that feare him.</hi> Fatherly and Motherlie loue, we know to bee verie great, and none know it, but they which are <hi>veri Patres,</hi> Fathers indéede, their bowels are mooued with more than an ordinarie affection toward their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as appeareth by the example of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, whoſe compaſſion was kindled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her childe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe heard ſentence giuen,<note place="margin">1, King, 3.26</note> and the ſword drawen to haue it diuided: God in like maner teſtifyeth. <hi>Hoſ. 8.11.</hi> that his hart is turned in him, &amp; that his repentance is rouled together, euen as a fathers doth: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he taketh in hand to puniſh his childe, he will beate him, and he will not beate him, loath he is, and therefore though he doeth it, hee doeth it vnwillingly, ſo doeth alſo our heauenly Father, he doth not puniſh vs with his heart, ſaieth <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations:<note place="margin">Lamen. 3, 33</note> but beſides this, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion farre excelleth, in that not onely it reacheth further than is poſſible for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny naturall affection to reach vnto: but alſo for that it is immutable, it neuer
<pb facs="tcp:17477:30"/> changeth. A mother may forget the fruit of her wombe: A Father may turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his face from his owne ſonne, and renownce him for euer. But though a <hi>woman ſhould forget the fruite of her wombe, yet would not forget thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa, 49.15,</note> ſaith the Lord, <hi>for I am the Lord and am not cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged:</hi> Therfore the Apoſtle ſaieth:<note place="margin">Rom, 11.2</note> 
               <hi>His gifts and callings are without repentance:</hi> And the Euangeliſt ſayeth, <hi>Iohn 13.1. Whome hee loueth, hee loueth vnto the ende.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And right Honorable and beloued, there is not a greater comfort vnto our ſoules and conſciences, in this our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent heauineſſe and diſtreſſe, than this: to conſider that hee is our Father that doeth thus correct vs, who though he be iuſtlie diſpleaſed with vs, and his wrath fore kindled againſt vs for our ſinnes: yet herein he ſheweth himſelfe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely gratious and mercifull vnto vs, in that hee hath taken the rod into his owne hand, &amp; not deliuered it into their handes that hate vs, to ſtrike vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>The Spaniards hath often hoped to
<pb facs="tcp:17477:31"/> haue got this rod into their hands, and haue as it were ſnatched, to haue pulled it vnto them, that they might haue bene Gods executioners. A bloudie day had that bene (beloued) for the corps, whom you haue ſéene, honorably and reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in peace caried to their graues, you ſhould haue ſéene them lying waltering in their bloud: in the middeſt of the ſtréets, torne with their Wyer whips, diſ-membred with their long Kniues: thruſt thorow with their ſharpe ſwords, and no man to haue buried them. Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents among our ſelues, as Papiſts and Atheſts had hoped to haue got this rod into their handes: and as by often Treaſons, againſt our late bleſſed So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, ſo by ſtronge conſpiracies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our now moſt gracious and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted King, whom God for euer kepe, from out of their handes, they haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted it.</p>
            <p>A day of horrour and confuſion, a blacke and diſmall day beloued, would that haue bene, for then, whereas now you kéepe your ſeates of honour (and for euer may you kéepe them) and euerie
<pb facs="tcp:17477:31"/> man poſſeſſeth his houſe and home in peace, and each neighbour ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his neighbour, and all may come with ſafetie to this place, and to other places of Gods worſhip to make their ſupplications before him: then, I ſaye, ye ſhould haue ſéene that verefied which is in the Prophecie of <hi>Eſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 3.5</note> 
               <hi>Nothing but oppreſsion and violence: Children preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt the ancient, and the vile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the honorable: Ephraim againſt Manaſſes, and Manaſſes againſt Ephraim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 9.21</note> 
               <hi>and both againſt Iudah.</hi> The Papiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Atheſt, &amp; the Atheſt againſt the Papiſt, &amp; both againſt the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour. You ſhould haue ſéene then, your houſes ranſacked, your wiues and your daughters diſhonoured, your ſwéete chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and babes, horriblie murthered, and euery mans ſworde imbrued in the bloud of his neighbour. Bleſſe we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and for euer bleſſe wee him, who hath not giuen vs as a praye vnto our enemies handes, but brought vpon their owne pates, the deſtruction &amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe they deuiſed for others. Himſelfe reſeruing the rod of our correction into
<pb facs="tcp:17477:32"/> his owne hand. And beſides, which alſo magnifyeth his loue excéedingly, taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rod to beate vs with, which is a more gentle and fauorable rod,<note place="margin">2. Sa, 24, 14,</note> than the reſt, as appeareth by the choice of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> who choſe rather to fall into the hands of God, then of man, who choſe rather the Peſtilence, then hunger. What wofull miſerie the ſworde of the enemie would haue brought, you haue heard: And I pray God, by experience, we may neuer know. What calamitie, famine and hunger cauſeth, you may eaſely conſider, when as it forceth to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine nature by vnnaturall foode, and the mother to féede vpon her yong babe.<note place="margin">1. King. 6.25.</note> Examples there are in this behalfe moſt lamentable, which I omit: In this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe wherewith the Lorde hath viſited vs, there is either a ſpéedie death and diſſolution, or a ſpéedie recouerie (for the moſt part) without languiſhing in long torment and paine, and much comforte ſéene in the quiet and milde yéelding vp of their ſpirits to God, whom hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and taketh to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Lord like a pittifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:17477:32"/> (for how ſhall I make an ende to ſpeake of his mercie that is endleſſe) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the onely promiſe of amendment, haue ſlacked his hand,<note place="margin">Exod, 34, 6, 7</note> to ſhewe and to manifeſt vnto vs, that he is full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and aboundant in compaſſion, and that if we will truly humble our ſelues, he hath done, and his wrath is paſt. As therefore yee haue begone, ſo continue your holie exerciſes of Preaching, of Prayer, &amp; of Faſting: &amp; that it may not be formall only and hypocritical, which the Lorde reprooueth ſo much in the Iewes. <hi>Is this the faſt that I haue choſen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa, 58.5, 6, 7</note> 
               <hi>that a man afflict his ſoule for a day, and hang downe his head like a Bull-ruſh?</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſubſtance of true faſting, <hi>is to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to let the oppreſſed goe free, to take off the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthen, and to breake euery yoke, To deale the bread to the hungrie, to bring the poore that wandreth into thy houſe: to couer the naked:</hi> and to doe ſuch other workes of mercie. And that which ſhall beſt pleaſe the Lord (right honorable) is, if by the ſworde of your authoritie, yee ſhall repreſſe the inſolencie of them, who
<pb facs="tcp:17477:33"/> not regarding the heauie hand of God, continue in their blaſphemie in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of the Sabaoth, in their drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, and in ſuch other deteſtable ſinnes, who ſay with the Epicure: <hi>Let vs eate, let vs drink, for to morrow we ſhal die:</hi> who make a pray &amp; a ſpoyle to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in this heauy time of ſicknes, by imbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeling of the goods of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be diſeaſed &amp; deceaſed, by defrauding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> widow, by defeating of the Orphanes, by robbing of the naturall kindred of their right. If ſuch complaints come before you (right Honorable) as I feare mee, many will: deferre not to do iuſtice: for if you do, the Lord will ſée it, and reuenge it: but if yee execute the iudgement of the Widow, and of the fatherleſſe: If you defende him that is oppreſſed, from the hande of him that oppreſſeth him: If you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the right, and puniſh the wrong: Then you ſhall ſée that God, who hath thus gratiouſly begunne, will euery day more and more ſlacke his hand, vntill he hath remooued this euill diſeaſe from you: then you ſhall ſée that hee who hath wounded you will heale you, then you
<pb facs="tcp:17477:33"/> ſhall ſée that he who hath in his anger for a moment viſited you, will in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting compaſſion embrace you, that you may ſée this your Citie againe peopled, by the ioyfull returne of your fellow ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, that are here and there diſperſed: that you may ſée thoſe ſeats, which are by you emptie, with the Honorable &amp; graue Iudges of the Lande, &amp; with your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull brethren repleniſhed: that you may ſée your trades and traffiquing which is now dead, to be renewed: that you may ſée your Tearmes and Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Lawe, no more omitted: that to conclude, you may ſée health and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie againe within your walles, &amp; that you may heare the voice of the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, and of the bride, and the noyſe of mirth and reioyſing, more than in the daies of good Quéene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it remaineth, that hauing thus farre forth diſcourſed of that high digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and preferment, whereunto we are aduanced, in being made the Sonnes of God, and heires of God, &amp; ioynt-heires with Ieſus Chriſt, the onely begotten and naturall Sonne of the Father of
<pb facs="tcp:17477:34"/> ſuch a celeſtiall and glorious kingdome, and hauing conſidered the original from whence ſo great mercy floweth vnto vs, which our Apoſtle ſheweth to bee the méere loue of God, which loue appeareth to be loue out of meaſure, Becauſe hee hath beſtowed it vpon vs that were his enemies, Becauſe he hath <hi>gratis</hi> and frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without our deſert giuen it vnto vs, Becauſe he hath giuen his only Sonne to death, to anſwere his iuſtice for vs, Becauſe he vouchſafeth to be called our Father, and more then our Father pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth vs, Correcting vs with his more gentle, and not with his ſharpeſt rod, &amp; repenting of the puniſhment before we repent vs of our ſinnes: It remaineth, I ſay, that wee procéede to the anſwere of the firſt obiection, which here enſueth: <hi>For this cauſe the worlde knoweth you not, becauſe it knoweth not him.</hi> But for that the time is ſpent: I muſt leaue the conſideration thereof, vnto your godly &amp; priuate Meditations, which I may the more ſafelie doe, hauing in ſuch ſort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed this holie and comfortable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine vnto you, as that all the obiections
<pb facs="tcp:17477:34"/> of man or Deuill, ſhall neuer be able to preuaile againſt it.</p>
            <p>And now, thou O Lord our God, which haſt in this wiſe ſo excéedingly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thy mercies vnto vs, in calling vs to be thy children: and haſt not for al our rebellions againſt thée, caſt vs off and vtterlie reiected vs, but chaſtized vs in great mercie for our ſinnes, and correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs for our tranſgreſſions; we beſéech thée to ſanctifie this thy fatherly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hande vnto vs, that wee may make right vſe thereof in louing thée for thy mercie, and fearing thée for thy iuſtice: That for the time of our life that remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, we may more religiouſly and more holily walke before thee in all godlineſſe of life and conuerſation. And to this end we praye thee to giue a bleſſing to the miniſterie, and Preaching of thy holy worde at this time: that gratiouſly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning, &amp; paſſing by whatſoeuer weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and infirmities haue bene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the ſpeaking &amp; hearing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thou wouldeſt pleaſe to make it effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall vnto vs, for the glorifying of thy name, for the edifying of our ſelues in
<pb facs="tcp:17477:35"/> faith, for the humbling of our ſoules by repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for the reforming of our liues from all vngodlineſſe, and ſo finally for the turning away of this thy feareful Plague and puniſhment, and for the purchaſing of thy wonted fauours, and bleſſings onto vs, and that for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our onely mediator and aduocate. To whome with thee and the holy Ghoſt three Perſons one true euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing and euerlaſting God, be rendred all praiſe, power, Dominion and thankſgiuing both now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17477:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
